NGINX JS DOM — Header and Body Filters

Overview

NGINX JS DOM lets JavaScript code intercept and transform every HTTP response that passes through a location. The interception happens at two points in nginx’s filter chain:

•

Header filters — called once, just before response headers are sent to the client. The callback receives the live NginxRequest object and may mutate response headers in place. The filter is always synchronous.

•

Body filters — called for each piece of the response body (streaming modes) or once on the complete body (whole-body modes). Four execution modes cover every combination of sync/async and chunk/whole: wholeBodySync, wholeBodyAsync, streamingSync, streamingAsync.

Filters are registered per-location via methods on the NginxLocation object (accessible through nginx.http.servers[i].locations[j] or by iterating nginx.http.servers[i].locations). Registering a filter from any script that runs at config time — js_source, js_init_http, js_preprocess — is sufficient; the filter then applies to every request that reaches that location.

Location filter API

All filter management methods live on the NginxLocation object.

2.1.location.addHeaderFilter(fn [, opts])

Appends a header-filter callback to the location’s header filter list.

location.addHeaderFilter(fn)
location.addHeaderFilter(fn, opts)

Returns undefined. Throws TypeError if fn is not a function.

2.2.location.addBodyFilter(mode, fn [, opts])

Appends a body-filter callback to the location’s body filter list.

location.addBodyFilter(mode, fn)
location.addBodyFilter(mode, fn, opts)

Returns undefined. Throws TypeError if mode is invalid or fn is not a function.

2.3.location.removeHeaderFilter(ref)

Removes the first header filter whose registered name equals ref (string) or whose function reference is === to ref. No-op if not found.

2.4.location.removeBodyFilter(ref)

Removes the first body filter matching ref by name or function reference. No-op if not found.

2.5.location.getHeaderFilter(ref)

Returns a descriptor object { name, priority, fn } for the first matching header filter, or null if not found.

2.6.location.getBodyFilter(ref)

Returns a descriptor object { name, priority, fn, mode } for the first matching body filter, or null if not found. mode is the string passed to addBodyFilter.

2.7.location.headerFilters(getter)

Returns a snapshot array of { name, priority, fn } objects for all currently registered header filters, in dispatch order.

2.8.location.bodyFilters(getter)

Returns a snapshot array of { name, priority, fn, mode } objects for all currently registered body filters, in dispatch order.

Filter options object

Both addHeaderFilter and addBodyFilter accept an optional second/third opts argument that controls where the new filter is inserted in the list:

{
name: string, // symbolic name — used by remove/get
priority: number, // lower = earlier; default 50
before: fn | string, // insert immediately before this filter
after: fn | string, // insert immediately after this filter
index: number // insert at this absolute position (0-based)
}

Precedence (highest first): index > before / after > priority.

If before or after references a filter that does not exist, the new filter is appended.

const upper = function(req, body) { return body.toUpperCase(); };
// append at default priority 50
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', upper);
// insert with a name so it can be removed later
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', upper, { name: 'uppercase' });
loc.removeBodyFilter('uppercase');
// insert before an existing filter
const wrap = function(req, body) { return '[' + body + ']'; };
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', wrap, { before: upper });
// insert at the beginning
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', wrap, { index: 0 });
// priority-based ordering: lower numbers run first
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', upper, { priority: 10 });
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', wrap, { priority: 20 });
// → upper runs first, then wrap

Header filter API

A header filter receives a single NginxRequest argument. At that point response headers are still mutable. Use standard property access on req:

function(req) {
// Read a response header
const type = req.getResponseHeader('content-type');
// Set/replace a response header
req.setResponseHeader('x-processed-by', 'nginx-js');
// Delete a response header
req.removeResponseHeader('server');
// Inspect the response status
const status = req.status; // number, e.g. 200
// Mutate the status before it is sent
req.status = 404;
}

Header filters are always synchronous. async function callbacks are accepted but any awaited operation completes after headers are already sent — do not rely on async behaviour inside a header filter.

The return value is ignored.

Body filter API

Whole-body modes (wholeBodySync,wholeBodyAsync)

The body is accumulated from all nginx chain links until last_buf is seen. Then the JS filter chain runs once on the complete body string.

// wholeBodySync — transform body synchronously
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
return body.toUpperCase(); // replace
// return undefined → pass through unchanged
});
// wholeBodyAsync — transform body after an async operation
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodyAsync', async function(req, body) {
const translated = await callTranslationService(body);
return translated; // replace
// return undefined → pass through unchanged
// throw new Error('...') → close the connection
});

Chaining: when multiple whole-body filters are registered they run in registration order; each filter receives the output of the previous one as its body argument.

Streaming modes (streamingSync,streamingAsync)

Streaming filters run on each chunk individually as nginx delivers it. The filter chain processes chunks in registration order.

4.2.1. streamingSync

Output is produced via req.sendBuffer(data). Multiple calls per invocation are allowed; their output is concatenated in call order and forwarded downstream. The next filter in the chain receives the concatenated output of the previous filter — not the original chunk.

location.addBodyFilter('streamingSync', function(req, chunk, flags) {
req.sendBuffer(chunk.toUpperCase()); // emit transformed chunk
// no call to sendBuffer → chunk is dropped
});

flags is an object with one property:

•

flags.last — true if this is the last chunk (corresponds to nginx’s last_buf flag).

4.2.2. streamingAsync

The filter returns a Promise. The resolved value determines the output:

Resolved value │ Effect

non-empty string │ Replace the chunk with this string

'' (empty string) │ Drop the chunk (emit nothing)

undefined / non-string │ Pass the chunk through unchanged

Rejection │ Close the connection with an error

req.sendBuffer() is not the output mechanism for streamingAsync — use the return value.

location.addBodyFilter('streamingAsync', async function(req, chunk, flags) {
await nginx.setTimeout(20); // simulate async work
return chunk.toUpperCase(); // replace
// return '' → drop
// return undefined / no return → pass through
// throw new Error('...') → close connection
});

4.3.req.sendBuffer(data)

Valid only inside a streamingSync filter callback. Appends data (coerced to string) to the current chunk’s output accumulator. Multiple calls per invocation are allowed.

If called outside a streamingSync context (i.e. inside a wholeBody* filter or outside any filter) it is a silent no-op and a WARN message is written to the error log.

4.4.flagsobject

Passed as the third argument to both streamingSync and streamingAsync callbacks:

{
last: boolean // true when this is the last chunk of the response
}

In mixed mode (see below) streaming filters receive the whole accumulated body as a single chunk with flags.last === true.

Mode selection (Mode A vs Mode B)

nginx JS DOM uses two internal dispatch strategies based on what filter types are registered for a location:

Mode │ When used │ Behaviour

Mode A — streaming │ Location has no wholeBody* filters │ nginx body-filter calls pass directly to the streaming chain; the body is never accumulated. Each call to nginx’s body filter = one call to each streaming filter.

Mode B — whole-body │ Location has at least one wholeBody* filter │ The body is fully accumulated, then ALL filters run in registration order on the complete body. streamingSync/streamingAsync filters in this list receive the whole body as a single last chunk.

The mode is selected automatically based on the filter list at request time. There is no explicit configuration knob.

Mixed mode (Mode B with streaming filters)

When both wholeBody* and streaming* filters share a location, Mode B is used and all filters run in registration order on the accumulated body. Streaming filters behave as follows:

•

streamingSync : called with (req, body, {last: true}). Emit output via req.sendBuffer(); no call → body is dropped.

•

streamingAsync : called with (req, body, {last: true}). Resolved string replaces the body; undefined passes through; '' drops it.

// Filter 1 (wholeBody): uppercase the body
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
return body.toUpperCase();
});
// Filter 2 (streaming): wrap in brackets — runs after filter 1
location.addBodyFilter('streamingSync', function(req, chunk, flags) {
req.sendBuffer('[' + chunk + ']');
});
// Request body 'hello' → 'HELLO' → '[HELLO]'

Execution order and chaining

Filters execute in the order they appear in the location’s filter list. Both header and body filter lists are independent.

// Header filter runs first, body filters run in order for each request
location.addHeaderFilter(function(req) {
req.setResponseHeader('x-stage', 'raw');
});
const step1 = function(req, body) { return body.trim(); };
const step2 = function(req, body) { return body.toUpperCase(); };
const step3 = function(req, body) { return '[' + body + ']'; };
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', step1);
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', step2);
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', step3);
// body passes through step1 → step2 → step3 in that order

Dynamic filter management

Filters can be added and removed at runtime from within a running filter callback. The implementation uses copy-on-write (COW) for the filter list: mutations during dispatch do not affect the current iteration but take effect for the next request.

let patched = false;
const firstRequest = function(req, body) {
if (!patched) {
// Add a second filter on the first request; takes effect on second
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
return body + ' (patched)';
});
patched = true;
}
return body;
};
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', firstRequest);

// Remove a named filter while it is running (safe — COW guarantees
// the current dispatch sees the old list)
const selfRemove = function(req, body) {
location.removeBodyFilter('once'); // removes itself
return body + ' [one-shot]';
};
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', selfRemove, { name: 'once' });

Priority and ordering

Filters added without an explicit index, before, or after option are inserted based on priority (lower = earlier, default 50):

// priority 10 runs before priority 20 runs before priority 50 (default)
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync',
(req, body) => body.trimStart(), { priority: 10 });
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync',
(req, body) => body.toUpperCase(), { priority: 20 });
location.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync',
(req, body) => '[' + body + ']'); // priority 50 (default)
// Order: trimStart → toUpperCase → bracket

Error handling

Situation │ Behaviour

wholeBodySync filter throws │ Exception is logged; body is passed through unchanged; next filter runs.

wholeBodyAsync filter rejects │ Error is logged; connection is closed (HTTP 500 or connection reset).

streamingSync filter throws │ Exception is logged; chunk is dropped; next filter runs.

streamingAsync filter rejects │ Error is logged; connection is closed.

addBodyFilter / addHeaderFilter called with wrong type │ TypeError is thrown immediately (synchronous, propagates to the caller).

Complete examples

Example 1 — Inject a banner into every HTML response

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(
function(l) { return l.path === '/'; }
);
// Modify the Content-Type header to ensure UTF-8
loc.addHeaderFilter(function(req) {
var ct = req.getResponseHeader('content-type') || '';
if (ct.indexOf('charset') === -1 && ct.indexOf('text/html') !== -1) {
req.setResponseHeader('content-type', ct + '; charset=utf-8');
}
});
// Inject a banner comment before </body>
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
var banner = '<!-- served by nginx-js -->';
return body.replace('</body>', banner + '</body>');
});
})();

Example 2 — GZIP-style response size logging

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations[0];
var totalBytes = 0;
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
totalBytes += body.length;
nginx.log('info', 'Response size: ' + body.length + ' bytes '
+ '(cumulative: ' + totalBytes + ')');
return undefined; // pass through unchanged
});
})();

Example 3 — Strip server-sent events containing a keyword

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(
function(l) { return l.path === '/events/'; }
);
// Per-chunk streaming: drop any SSE event containing 'internal'
loc.addBodyFilter('streamingSync', function(req, chunk, flags) {
if (chunk.indexOf('internal') !== -1) {
return; // no sendBuffer → drop this chunk
}
req.sendBuffer(chunk);
});
})();

Example 4 — Async translation (wholeBodyAsync)

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(
function(l) { return l.path === '/translate/'; }
);
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodyAsync', async function(req, body) {
// nginx.setTimeout returns a Promise that resolves after ms
await nginx.setTimeout(0); // yield to event loop
// Simulate async translation (replace with a real upstream fetch)
var translated = body.split('hello').join('hola');
return translated;
});
})();

Example 5 — Async per-chunk watermark injection (streamingAsync)

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(
function(l) { return l.path === '/stream/'; }
);
loc.addBodyFilter('streamingAsync', async function(req, chunk, flags) {
await nginx.setTimeout(0); // yield to event loop
if (flags.last) {
// Append a watermark to the last chunk
return chunk + '\n<!-- end of stream -->';
}
return chunk; // pass through other chunks unchanged
});
})();

Example 6 — Chained pipeline: streaming bracket + async uppercase

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations[0];
// Step 1: synchronously wrap each chunk in angle brackets
loc.addBodyFilter('streamingSync', function(req, chunk, flags) {
req.sendBuffer('<' + chunk + '>');
});
// Step 2: asynchronously uppercase (receives step 1 output as input)
loc.addBodyFilter('streamingAsync', async function(req, chunk, flags) {
await nginx.setTimeout(5);
return chunk.toUpperCase(); // '<hello>' → '<HELLO>'
});
})();

Example 7 — Priority-based middleware stack

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations[0];
// Security: strip internal headers — run first (priority 10)
loc.addHeaderFilter(function(req) {
req.removeResponseHeader('x-internal-token');
req.removeResponseHeader('x-debug-info');
}, { priority: 10 });
// Observability: add timing header — run last (priority 90)
var started = Date.now();
loc.addHeaderFilter(function(req) {
req.setResponseHeader('x-response-ms',
String(Date.now() - started));
}, { priority: 90 });
// Body: redact PII — normal priority (50)
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
return body.replace(/\b\d{4}-\d{4}-\d{4}-\d{4}\b/g, '****-****-****-****');
});
})();

Example 8 — One-shot filter that installs itself then removes itself

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations[0];
// Fires only on the first request, then removes itself
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function firstOnly(req, body) {
loc.removeBodyFilter(firstOnly);
return '<!-- first request -->\n' + body;
}, { name: 'first-only' });
})();

Example 9 — Mixed mode: WB normalize then streaming chunk markers

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(
function(l) { return l.path === '/api/'; }
);
// Filter 1 (wholeBodySync): parse JSON and re-serialize normalized
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
try {
var obj = JSON.parse(body);
return JSON.stringify(obj); // compact, keys sorted by JS engine
} catch (e) {
return undefined; // pass through if not JSON
}
});
// Filter 2 (streamingAsync): add a Content-Length annotation asynchronously
// Receives the normalized body as a single chunk (flags.last === true)
loc.addBodyFilter('streamingAsync', async function(req, chunk, flags) {
await nginx.setTimeout(0);
return chunk + '\n/* length: ' + chunk.length + ' */';
});
})();

Example 10 — Runtime conditional filter (A/B test)

(function() {
var loc = nginx.http.servers[0].locations[0];
var featureEnabled = false;
// Toggle can be flipped externally via a SharedWorker or another
// request handler that has access to the same closure.
function enableFeature() { featureEnabled = true; }
function disableFeature() { featureEnabled = false; }
loc.addBodyFilter('wholeBodySync', function(req, body) {
if (!featureEnabled) {
return undefined; // pass through when A/B flag is off
}
return '<div class="beta">' + body + '</div>';
});
// Expose control surface via a separate management location
var mgmt = nginx.http.servers[0].locations.find(
function(l) { return l.path === '/admin/feature/'; }
);
if (mgmt) {
mgmt.handler = function(req) {
var enable = req.uri.indexOf('?enable') !== -1;
if (enable) { enableFeature(); } else { disableFeature(); }
req.respond(200, {}, 'feature ' + (featureEnabled ? 'ON' : 'OFF'));
};
}
})();

Reference summary

Location methods

Method │ Returns │ Description

addHeaderFilter(fn [, opts]) │ undefined │ Register a header-filter callback.

addBodyFilter(mode, fn [, opts]) │ undefined │ Register a body-filter callback.

removeHeaderFilter(ref) │ undefined │ Remove a header filter by name or function reference.

removeBodyFilter(ref) │ undefined │ Remove a body filter by name or function reference.

getHeaderFilter(ref) │ {name, priority, fn} or null │ Retrieve header filter descriptor.

getBodyFilter(ref) │ {name, priority, fn, mode} or null │ Retrieve body filter descriptor.

headerFilters (getter) │ Array of {name, priority, fn} │ Snapshot of all header filters in dispatch order.

bodyFilters (getter) │ Array of {name, priority, fn, mode} │ Snapshot of all body filters in dispatch order.

Body filter modes

Mode string │ Signature │ Output mechanism

'wholeBodySync' │ fn(req, body) → string|undefined │ Return value

'wholeBodyAsync' │ async fn(req, body) → Promise<string|undefined> │ Resolved value of returned Promise

'streamingSync' │ fn(req, chunk, flags) │ req.sendBuffer(data) — zero or more calls

'streamingAsync' │ async fn(req, chunk, flags) → Promise<string|undefined> │ Resolved value of returned Promise

11.3.req.sendBuffer(data)

Parameter │ Description

data │ String (or coercible to string) to append to the current chunk output.

Valid only inside a streamingSync callback. No-op + WARN log in all other contexts.

Filter options object

Property │ Type │ Description

name │ string │ Symbolic name for later remove / get calls. Optional.

priority │ number │ Insertion priority. Lower = earlier. Default 50. Used when no positional option (index, before, after) is given.

index │ number │ Absolute 0-based insertion position. Takes precedence over all other options.

before │ function or string │ Insert immediately before this filter (matched by function reference or name).

after │ function or string │ Insert immediately after this filter (matched by function reference or name).

11.5.flagsobject (streaming callbacks)

Property │ Type │ Description

last │ boolean │ true if this is the final chunk of the response body.